Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Media collection, 1923-1999 MVC0044.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Media collection
1925-1999
1946-1999
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0044.MS
5 Linear Feet 2 over-size video tape boxes, 1 flat box, 2 letter-size document boxes, 12 film cans
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999. This collection contains videotapes, audio cassettes, audio tape reels, 8 mm film, 16 mm film, and a 35 mm film from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives. The recordings capture campus scenes, ceremonies, celebrations, and student life predominately on the Spring Valley and Foxhall Road campuses of Mount Vernon Seminary and College. They range in date from 1925 to 1999, with the bulk of the media dating between 1946 and 1999.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains videotapes, audio cassettes, audio tape reels, 8 mm film, 16 mm film, and a 35 mm film from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives. The recordings capture campus scenes, ceremonies, celebrations, and student life predominately on the Spring Valley and Foxhall Road campuses of Mount Vernon Seminary and College. They range in date from 1925 to 1999, with the bulk of the media dating between 1946 and 1999.
Biographical / Historical
The Mount Vernon Seminary began in 1875 as a private high school and junior college for women, founded by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999.
The first school of higher education available to women in Washington, D.C., Mount Vernon Seminary and College had five different locations throughout its history:
1875-1880: Elizabeth Somers began tutoring the young daughters of prominent Washington men in her home at 204 F Street, NW in Washington, DC.
1880-1917: The school moved to 1100 M Street, NW where it expanded rapidly to include three additional houses, a courtyard, tennis court, and basketball court.
1917-1942: Having outgrown its M Street location, the school moved to a 15.5-acre campus on Nebraska Avenue, NW. The buildings and layout of the campus were designed by a New York architect, Wesley S. Bessell. and the campus was formally dedicated on November 5, 1917 -- Mrs. Somers' 80th birthday. In 1942, the United States Navy took over the Nebraska Avenue campus to use its facilities for the war effort.
1943-1946: The school resumed courses in February 1943 at the top floor of a Garfinckel's department store building in the Spring Valley neighborhood of Washington, D.C.
1946-1999: Between 1944 and 1946, the school built a new 21-acre campus located on Foxhall Road in Washington, D.C. using money granted to the college by the United States Navy in compensation for the military takeover of its property.
The last Seminary class graduated in 1969, and the school was then officially renamed to Mount Vernon Junior College. In 1976, Mount Vernon College became an accredited four year college. In 1997, the Board of Trustees decided that the College would close as an independent institution. As of June 30, 1999, Mount Vernon became affiliated with The George Washington University.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: Films, Videos, Audio Cassettes, and Audio Tape Reels.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Mount Vernon Seminary and College archives were acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. The collection was transferred to the Foggy Bottom campus in 2009.
Bib#
8821938
Audiovisual material; Audiocassettes; Audiotapes; Black-and-white film; Color film; Women -- Education; Videocassettes; Women's colleges; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College
- Films, 1925-1968; 1946-1956; Series 1; 24 media 24 film cans
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by film gauge, beginning with 16 mm films, then the 35 mm film, and finally the 8 mm films.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains silent 16 mm and 8 mm films, and one 35 mm film. The films depict campus scenes, ceremonies, celebrations, and student life predominately on the Spring Valley and Foxhall Road campuses of Mount Vernon Seminary and College. They range in date from 1925 to 1968, with the bulk of the films dating between 1946 and 1956. Of note are Films 13 and 19 capturing Mount Vernon Seminary's fiftieth anniversary Golden Jubilee celebrations; the centenary celebration of the birth of Mount Vernon Seminary founder, Elizabeth J. Somers, in Film 1; and Foxhall Road campus groundbreaking, construction, and dedication ceremonies in Films 9, 14, 15, 17, and 18.
  - Parade of the Years, Elizabeth Somers Centenary. Mount Vernon Seminary., 1937; Series 1 (Film can 1, Film 1)
    Appears to be a fashion show of historic clothing.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    16 mm, Silent, Color (Kodak Panchromatic), Diacetate, Reversal, 100 ft.
  - Horseback Riding. Mount Vernon Seminary., circa 1937; Series 1 (Film can 1, Film 2)
    Subjects: Women riding horses - long-distance shot. Two women in a dormitory room, reading and listening to a radio.
    16 mm, Silent, Color (Kodak Panchromatic), Diacetate, Reversal, 20 ft.
  - Foxhall Road campus scenes, May 1956; Series 1 (Film can 1, Film 3)
    Subjects: Buildings, Tennis courts, Students socializing at a picnic table, Student painting outdoors.
    16 mm, Silent, Color (Kodachrome), Triacetate, Reversal, 50 ft.
  - Great Falls Picnic, Mount Vernon Seminary, 1941; Series 1 (Film can 1, Film 4)
    Film by Frances Woodruff.
    Subjects: Students boarding bus, Scenic views of Great Falls, Students hiking, Food being prepared, Buildings on Mount Vernon Seminary campus (Nebraska Avenue campus?).
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Diacetate, Reversal, 50 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Clay Sculpture Class, 1966-1968; Series 1 (Film can 2, Film 5)
    16 mm, Silent, single perf, Black and White, Triacetate, Reversal, 100 ft.
  - Advertisements for Jack Waldron's Mount Vernon Print Shop and for Modern Home Insulations, unknown; Series 1 (Film can 2, Film 6)
    Advertisements for Cinema Art Club taught by William Joe Rogers; Jack Wladron's Mount Vernon Print Shop, 1005 9th Street, NW; and Modern Home Insulations.
    16 mm, Silent, Black and White, Diacetate, Reversal, 100 ft.
  - Students playing basketball, coming and going with suitcases, circa 1948; Series 1 (Film can 2, Film 7)
    Subjects: Outdoor basketball game vs. boys; Students walking in and out of buildings carrying suitcases, loading and unloading taxis and cars.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 100 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Campus Turf Club Carnival, circa 1955; Series 1 (Film can 2, Film 8)
    Subjects: Party and outdoor games, Brief interior shot of library?
    16 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, Reversal, 50 ft.
  - Great Hall Cornerstone Laying Ceremony, Foxhall Road campus, November 1956; Series 1 (Film can 3, Film 9)
    Subjects: Stage, Audience, Mount Vernon College students wearing white blazers.
  - May Day Celebration, May 1952; Series 1 (Film can 3, Film 10)
    Subjects: Procession and crowning of May Queen and her court, Dancing, Maypole.
  - Mount Vernon Junior College May Pageant, 1957; Series 1 (Film can 3, Film 11)
    16mm, Silent, Color (Kodachrome), Triacetate, Reversal, 50 ft.
  - MVS, Here's To You, 1966; Series 1 (Film can 4, Film 12)
    Mount Vernon Seminary senior class, 1966. Film made by students featuring student life on Foxhall Road campus.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 300 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Golden Jubilee Celebration, 23 May 1925; Series 1 (Film can 5, Film 13)
    Mount Vernon Seminary celebrates its fiftieth anniversary.
    16 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, A Wind Dupe Negative, 400 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College Spring Valley campus scenes and commencement ceremony, Foxhall Road campus groundbreaking, and winter fieldtrip [1/2], circa 1945-1946; Series 1 (Film can 6, Film 14)
    Subjects: Buildings on Spring Valley campus; Commencement ceremony, 1945; Sign communicating site of new Mount Vernon College buildings on Foxhall Road campus, 1946; Students looking at blueprints and drawings for Foxhall Road campus; Foxhall Road campus dedication ceremony; Students roasting marshmallows and hotdogs in outdoor fireplace; Students playing field hockey; Students playing tennis; Students in front of Christmas decorations; Bulletin board display about bacteria; Winter trip including skiing, skating, hiking, hotel, dining room, and loading of bus.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 375 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College fieldtrips, commencement ceremony at Metropolitan Methodist Church, and laying of cornerstone on Foxhall Road campus, 1946 [2/2], Series 1 (Film can 7, Film 15)
    Subjects: Winter ski trip including skiing, sledding, and cook-out; Fieldtrip to downtown Washington, D.C. and garden; Procession for commencement ceremony at Metropolitan Methodist Church; Laying of Cornerstone on Foxhall Road campus, June 3, 1946.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Tiracetate, Reversal, 350 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College student life, circa 1948; Series 1 (Film can 8, Film 16)
    Subjects: Fieldtrip; Procession and outdoor ceremony - tree planting?; Students playing softball and tennis; Student president campaign signs; Students walking on campus, sunbathing; Classes being conducted outdoors; Dog in flower bed on campus; Fashion show; Commencement; Horseback riding.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College Foxhall Road campus construction and facilities, circa 1946; Series 1 (Film can 9, Film 17)
    Subjects: Foxhall Road campus construction, Students in classroom, Campus in snow, Dining hall, Dormitory room, Student lounge, Library, Science lab, Art studio.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 350 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College students at church, construction of Acheson Hall, and student ringing Ames bell, circa 1950; Series 1 (Film can 10, Film 18)
    Subjects: Students visiting the Metropolitan Methodist Church, Construction of Acheson hall, Shots of Foxhall Road campus, Student ringing Anne Seymour Ames bell.
    16 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 100 ft., Beginning is dark.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Golden Jubilee Celebration, 23 May 1925; Series 1 (Film can 11, Film 19)
    Mount Vernon Seminary celebrates its fiftieth anniversary. This film is longer and has more content than the 16 mm copy.
    35 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, Positive, 1,000 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College Winter Fieldtrip, circa 1948; Series 1 (Film can 12, Film 20)
    Subjects: Ice skating, Hiking, Group of students lined up on front steps of a building.
    8 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, Positive, 50 ft.
  - Ride Around Mount Vernon Seminary and College Foxhall Road campus, Girls Wave, circa 1948-1955; Series 1 (Film can 3, Film 21)
    8 mm, Silent, Color, Triacetate, Reversal, 25 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Field Hockey, circa 1946; Series 1 (Film can 12, Film 22)
    Subjects: Students in athletic uniforms, Students playing field hockey, Students holding "Yellow" team banner for intramural sports, Students playing with pet goat and pig (mascots?).
    8 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, Reversal, 50 ft.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary campus scenes, circa 1947; Series 1 (Film can 12, Film 23)
    Subjects: Mount Vernon Seminary students and faculty walking on campus, Students playing outdoor volleyball, Campus in snow and students playing in snow, Sleigh ride, Student in canoe.
  - Mount Vernon Seminary and College Roller Skating, Dancing, and Swimming, circa 1945; Series 1 (Film can 12, Film 24)
    8 mm, Silent, Black and White, Triacetate, Reversal, 50 ft., Very dark at end.
- Videos, 1987-1999; Series 2; 31 media 2 over-size video boxes
  This series contains VHS and betacam videotapes. The videos depict ceremonies, celebrations, and other special events on the Foxhall Road campus of Mount Vernon College. Subjects include the dedication ceremony for Eckles Library, the inauguration of President LucyAnn Geiselman, convocations, baccalaureates, commencements, Founder's Day celebrations, and Symposia on Women in Politics and Journalism. They range in date from 1987 to 1999.
  Arranged chronologically, with undated videos at the end of the sequence.
  - Mount Vernon College Library Dedication, 18 September 1987; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 1)
    VHS
  - Bacchalaureate, 11 June 1988; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 2)
  - Mount Vernon College commencement, 14 May 1989; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 3)
  - Mount Vernon College convocation, 14 September 1989; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 4)
  - Founder's Day Celebration, Nien Cheng speaker, 10 November 1989; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 5)
  - Baccalaureate, 12 May 1990; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 6)
  - Founder's Day, 10 November 1990; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 7)
  - Scenes of Mount Vernon College and Segments of Baccalaureate, 10 May 1991 - 11 May 1991; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 8)
  - Mount Vernon College Commencement, 12 May 1991; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 9)
  - Academic Symposium, "Women in the Academy", 17 September 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 10)
  - Inauguration of President LucyAnn Geiselman [1/4], 18 September 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 11)
    Betacam
  - Inauguration of President LucyAnn Geiselman [2/4], 18 September 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 12)
  - Inauguration of President LucyAnn Geiselman [3/4], 18 September 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 13)
  - Inauguration of President LucyAnn Geiselman [4/4], 18 September 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 14)
  - Mount Vernon College Residence Program, Metro Report, News 8 Cable, 18 December 1992; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 15)
    VHS, 56 seconds
  - Symposium on Women in Politics and Journalism, 28 September 1993; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 16)
  - Symposium on Women in Politics and Journalism, 13 September 1994; Series 2 (Oversize 1, Videocassette 17)
    VHS, 1 hour
  - Baccalaureate, 6 May 1995; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 1)
    VHS, 58 minutes
  - Mount Vernon College Commencement, 7 May 1995; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 2)
  - Symposium of Women in Politics and Journalism, 28 September 1995; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 3)
  - Linda Wilkins Junior Honors in Celebration of Prestigious African-American Women, and "Collaborations, Too", 18 April 1996 - 19 April 1996; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 4)
  - The 124th Graduating Class of Mount Vernon College, 1999; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 5)
  - The 124th Graduating Class of Mount Vernon College, 1999; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 6)
  - The 124th Graduating Class of Mount Vernon College, 1999; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 7)
  - Success Mount Vernon Style, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 8)
    VHS, Final Master
  - Hillwood Museum, The Collection of Marjorie Merriweather Post, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 9)
  - Mount Vernon College, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 10)
  - Mount Vernon College, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 11)
  - Mount Vernon College, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 12)
  - Mount Vernon College, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 13)
  - Mount Vernon College, unknown; Series 2 (Oversize 2, Videocassette 14)
- Audio Cassettes, 1961-1999 and unknown; 1972-1999; Series 3; 21 media 1 flat box
  This series contains audio tape cassettes. The tapes capture campus ceremonies, celebrations, and special events on the Foxhall Road campus of Mount Vernon Seminary and College, particularly commencement ceremonies. They range in date from 1961 to 1999, with the bulk of the tapes dating between 1972 and 1999.
  Arranged chronologically with undated tapes at the end of the sequence.
  - "A School Which Hath Foundations" Founder's Day Address by Mrs. George Lloyd, 2 November 1961; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 1)
  - Promotional tape, circa 1970-1972; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 2)
  - Convocation, 1976; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 3)
  - Vice President Rockefeller, chapel, 14 December 1976; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 4)
  - Convocation, 1977; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 5)
  - Commencement, 7 June 1987; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 6)
  - Commencement, 12 June 1988; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 7)
  - Convocation, August 1988; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 8)
  - Mount Vernon College Alma Mater, Voice and Piano, Stanzas 1-4, 1988; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 9)
  - Convocation, Guest Speaker David Brankly, 13 September 1990; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 10)
  - Founder's Day, 8 November 1990; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 11)
  - Graduation [1/2], 1995; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 12)
  - Graduation [2/2], 1995; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 13)
  - Commencement, 5 May 1996; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 14)
  - Commencement [1/2], 1998; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 15)
  - Commencement [2/2], 1998; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 16)
  - Walter Beach, 6 August 1999; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 17)
  - Business Office Slide Show Soundtrack, unknown; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 18)
  - Arts and Humanities, unknown; Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 19)
  - Unknown, Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 20)
  - Unknown, Series 3 (Flat box 1, Cassette 21)
- Audio Tape Reels, circa 1950-1975; 1968-1975; Series 4; 11 media 2 document boxes
  Arranged by size (7-inch, 5-inch, 3-inch), then chronologically.
  This series contains audio tape reels. The tapes capture campus ceremonies, celebrations, and special events on the Foxhall Road campus. They range in date from 1950 to 1975, with the bulk of the tapes dating between 1968 and 1975. Of note is a recording of the 1970 dedication ceremony for the Florence Hollis Hand Chapel.
  - Presentation of Architect, Master Site Plan, circa 1950; Series 4 (Box 1, Reel 1)
    7-inch reel, 3 3/4 ips
  - Convocation, 1973; Series 4 (Box 1, Reel 2)
    7-inch reel
  - Mount Vernon College Childhood Education Conference, 17 May 1975; Series 4 (Box 1, Reel 3)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Chimes [1/2], unknown; Series 4 (Box 1, Reel 4)
  - Mount Vernon Seminary Chimes, Pre-Lent, Lent, and Easter [2/2], unknown; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 1)
  - Mrs. George W. Lloyd's Address on the History of Mount Vernon Seminary. Mount Vernon Seminary joint chapel., 1 November 1961; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 2)
    5-inch reel
  - Founder's Day, 5 November 1975; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 3)
  - Address to the Graduating Class, Frank Farmer, Ph.D., President, Federal City College, 3 June 1968; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 4)
    3-inch reel, 3 3/4 ips, Mono.
    Speakers: Mr. Pelham, Mrs. Holland, student president
  - 95th Founder's Day Convocation, 5 November 1969; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 5)
    3-inch reel, 15 minutes.
  - Chapel Dedication, 2 November 1970; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 6)
    3-inch reel, 10 minutes.
  - "Mount Vernon Past and Present" Soundtrack for Alumnae Luncheon Slideshow, 5 June 1971; Series 4 (Box 2, Reel 7)
    3-inch reel, 7 1/2 ips, Mono, 2 tracks, Spliced, Side 2 blank.
    From original box:
    Creator and performer: J. Schubert.
    Old piano music from silent film era accompanies old Mount Vernon College slides. "New" sound of Hollywood fanfare accompanies the "new look" of Mount Vernon College. Voiceover leads into the question, "Where do we go from here?" Show used as intro to President's pitch on current conditions at Mount Vernon College.